<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A compend of chronography: containing four thousand thirty yeers complet, from Adams creation to Christs birth. As an harbinger to two larger tomes, in pawn of the authors promiss: which he intends to perform, if God shal permit. / By Rob. Vilvain of Excester. Price at press 3 d.</title>
            <author>Vilvain, Robert, 1575?-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1654</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A95922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V394</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E897_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206719</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865832</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865832</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118083</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A95922)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118083)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 135:E897[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A compend of chronography: containing four thousand thirty yeers complet, from Adams creation to Christs birth. As an harbinger to two larger tomes, in pawn of the authors promiss: which he intends to perform, if God shal permit. / By Rob. Vilvain of Excester. Price at press 3 d.</title>
                  <author>Vilvain, Robert, 1575?-1663.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 9 [i.e. 17] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Hodgkinsonne (for the author) and are to be sold at his house in Thames street, neer Baynards Castle,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>an. Dom. 1654.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Leaf 17 misnumbered 9.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb 28 1656";"came not [to] hand till now".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  History of Biblical events --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Chronology.</term>
               <term>History --  Study and teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>History --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:118083:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A COMPEND</hi> OF CHRONOGRAPHY: Containing <hi>Four thouſand thirty yeers complet, from</hi> Adams <hi>Creation to Chriſts Birth.</hi> As an Harbinger to two larger Tomes, in pawn of the Authors promiſſ: which he intends to perform, if God ſhal permit.</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tempus edax Rerum: quae Tempus edit mala Res eſt.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Time al things doth devour or ſpil: </l>
                  <l>The thing which time miſpends is il.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>By ROB. VILVAIN of <hi>Exceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Price at Preſſ 3 d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>R. Hodgkinſonne</hi> (for the Author) and are to be ſold at his Houſe in <hi>Thames ſtreet,</hi> neer <hi>Baynards Caſtle An. Dom.</hi> 1654.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118083:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:118083:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:118083:3"/>
            <head>A Prefatiuncle.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHronography is a new term, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act examen of Times from the beginning to Chriſts birth an unuſual thing: but both very proper or pertinent to imply the Authors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions. Which having ſuccinctly ſignified, ſhal ſuffice to giv a litle glimpſ of light, in the dark crooked corners of this intricat Labyrinth: enough to lead the wandring ſteps of Novice Chronologers in a right courſ.</hi> Adieu.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118083:3"/>
            <head>CHRONOGRAPHY.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>HRONOLOGY is a collation or <note place="margin">Definitions.</note> coordination of things doon in time, or applied therto: of which kind are many learned works every wher extant. Chronography a diſcuſſion or diſquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Times themſelfs: which are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raly ſtated by ſom in certain peecemeal parcels, but by none intirely together.</p>
            <p>Times (to omit Philoſophers Phyſical partition into paſt, <note place="margin">Preamble.</note> preſent, future) are diverſly divided: 1. With Aſtronomers into yeers (Solar and Lunar) moneths (of Peragration in 27. dais 8. hours, wherin the Moon runs hir race through the Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diac; conſtitution in 28. dais or 4. weeks, ordained for Mens affairs, and Conſecution in 29. dais, 12. hours 44. minuts, wherin the Moon at Conjuction overtakes the Sun) weeks (Diarian of 7. natural dais, and Annarian of 7. Solar yeers) dais (natural of 24. equal hours, and Artificial of 12. unequal from Sunriſing to ſetting) hours (Equinoctial of 60. minuts, and unequal according to the dimenſions of Artificial dais) minuts 60. in an hour, and ſecunds or ſections 60. in a minut: which is not ſo pertinent to this purpoſe. 2. With the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles into times of old (reaching from the Creation to Chriſts coming) and the laſt dais extending to the Worlds end: which large exception ſutes not with this intention. 3. With Rabbi <hi>Elias</hi> into 3. Diſchiliads; that as the World was made in 6. dais, ſo it ſhal dure 6000. yeers; <hi>Becauſ one</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 8. <hi>Pſ</hi> 90. 4.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:118083:4"/> 
               <hi>day with the Lord is as</hi> 1000. <hi>yeers: viz.</hi> 2000. before the Law of Circumciſion commenced in <hi>Abraham,</hi> caled void becauſ few Kingdoms were erected, and the Earth thinly Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled: 2000. under it, which Chriſt fulfilled in the fleſh and finiſhed: 2000. under the Meſſias or Goſpel, which none can preſcribe or prefine: but this diſtribution is too groſſ and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tru. 4. With learned <hi>Varro</hi> into Claſſic ſpaces: <hi>viz.</hi> from the Worlds origin to <hi>Ogyges</hi> Flood, which he cals <hi>Adyla,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, or dubious: from thence to the Olympiads ſtiled mythica, or fabulous: and the reſt downward to al ages, caled hiſtorical, fiducious, or veracious: but this rather reſpects the quality then quantity of time. 5. With the Fathers and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines into ſeveral Ages grounded on ſet periods in ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; with ſom ſort into ſix, ſom into ſeven ſections according to the dais of Creation, ſuting beſt with my occaſion: but this deſign from the Creation to Chriſts birth ſhal be branched into ten ſuch Stages or Stations: <hi>trahit ſua quem<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> voluntas.</hi> For every Man abounds in his own ſenſ, and proponeth a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod moſt complacently conſonant to his own phanſy or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.</p>
            <p>The firſt Stage from <hi>Adams</hi> creation to the Floods inchoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <note place="margin">1 Stage in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluds 1656. <hi>Gen. ch.</hi> 7. and 8.</note> contains 1656 Solar yeers (as appeers in the continuance therof ſo many months and dais, as make up an intire yeer) not Lunar, of 30 dais only, as ſom ſenſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly ſuppoſe; for no Nation ever uſed ſuch ſav the old Egyptians, nor they in Civil matters (as <hi>Cenſorinus</hi> avers) but their Prieſts in ſacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticals, to amplify a beleef of their antiquity among credulous People. This period is proved by the Protopatriarchs gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of Sons: <hi>For Adam lived</hi> 130. <hi>ful out (ſo 'tis meant of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5 per totum.</note> 
               <hi>al the reſt) and begot</hi> Seth: <hi>he at</hi> 105. Enos: <hi>he at</hi> 90. Cainan: <hi>he at</hi> 70. Mahalaleel: <hi>he at</hi> 65. Jared: <hi>he at</hi> 162. Enoch: <hi>he at</hi> 65. Michuſelah: <hi>he at</hi> 187. Lamech: <hi>he at</hi> 182. Noah: <hi>he at</hi> 600. <hi>entred the Arc: in al</hi> 1656. The 72. Elders ſtiled ſeptuagints (or haply their Scribes) exceed the ſaid ſum 706. yeers after the Greec Tranſlation, or 586. in the Latin; which palpably prevaricats from <hi>Moſes</hi> Hebrew Prototype: yet moſt Antients folow them as reverend holy Men; but the Man of God muſt be preferred to a million of Godly Men.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:118083:4"/>
            <p>He that wil be Truths Champion in Chronical compute, tho a deſpicable Dwarf; may not yeeld an inch to the greateſt Giant: no not in a difference of one yeers dimenſion. <hi>Joſeph Scaliger</hi> was ſingularly skild in moſt Sciences, but ſelf weening (as beſt wits are) and ſubject to errors. In points of Chronography, he is rather a troubler then amender of accompts, as <hi>Salianus</hi> ſtiles him: who to ſeem curious or cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious in mites, conteſts about one yeer (as <hi>Henry Hotſpur</hi> with <hi>Owen Glendower</hi> about Trents torted turnings, in their imaginary ſortition or ſharing of <hi>England)</hi> that the Flood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan A 1657. current, becauſ 'tis ſaid, <hi>Noah was</hi> 600 <hi>complet,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 7 6.</note> 
               <hi>when the waters were on the Earth:</hi> yet the very words plainly purport the being, not beginning of that Deluge: yea 'tis after cleered, <hi>that in the</hi> 600. <hi>current of his life, the fountains</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ibid v.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>of the great Deep broke up:</hi> So the places are eaſily reconciled, tho one miſtaken. Indeed the Fathers are ſaid to liv, ſo many yeers (meaning complet) and beget Children, which Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nologers interpret of their Births: and haply the fractions which they lived longer, may ſomwhat exced the ſaid ſum. For the holy Ghoſt is not ſcrupulous in ſuch ſcantlings; which being incertain, we muſt reckon no more nor leſſ then is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in the Genealogy. Som ſtifly ſtriv that al were born juſt at the yeers end; which is moſt improbable, that al ſhould be born on the 6. day as <hi>Adam</hi> was created: and ſo let it paſſ for an inconſiderable trifle ſcarſly to be conceived or credited. For the od over-plus of moneths or dais, may more ſafely be omitted or excluded, and the preciſe ſum of 1656. yeers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dubitably received.</p>
            <p>The ſecund from <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood to <hi>Abrams</hi> Birth includs <note place="margin">2 Stage 353.</note> 353. yeers, aſſerted by the Poſtpatriarchs begetting of Sons: <hi>For the Deluge dured one yeer, and Sem begot Arphaxad two</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 8. 13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. 10.</note> 
               <hi>yeers after it ended: he Salah at</hi> 35.: <hi>he Eber at</hi> 30. <hi>he Peleg at</hi> 34.: <hi>he Reu at</hi> 30.: <hi>he Sarug at</hi> 32.: <hi>he Nahor at</hi> 36.: <hi>he Terah at</hi> 29.: <hi>he Abram at</hi> 130.: <hi>in al</hi> 353. The ſeventy tranſlators or their tranſcribers, not only ad 700. yeers to 7. of thoſ Patriarchs: but inſert one <hi>Cainan Arphaxads</hi> ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Son (haply miſpriſed or miſplaced for <hi>Enos</hi> Son. Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to <hi>Adam)</hi> giving him 130. yeers yer he begot <hi>Salah:</hi> but
<pb facs="tcp:118083:5"/> 
               <hi>Moſes</hi> mentions no ſuch Man, nor doo the Chronicles name <note place="margin">1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 1. 18. <hi>Luke</hi> 3. 36.</note> him. St. <hi>Luke</hi> (whoſ tranſcribers folow the ſeptuagints) cites him, yet haply not the Original: for neither <hi>Philo,</hi> nor <hi>Joſephus,</hi> nor St. <hi>Jerom</hi> or any of the Antients writing on his Genealogy, take notice of <hi>Cainan</hi> in the ſeventy or Evangeliſt: therfore 'tis probable that both are vitiated ſince their times. Yea <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith <hi>Cainan</hi> is caſhired in an old Manuſcript of his: yet did il to omit him in his tranſlation, being generaly received in al Copies. Howbeit ſith <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Chronicles exclude him, he may not be included in ſacred Chronology. For if <hi>Moſes</hi> loſt him, wher did the 70. find him, who had al their light from him, being but his Torch-bearers or Tranſlators?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Salianus</hi> ſaith <hi>Moſes</hi> ſuppreſſed him to make the Patriarchs two Decads (before and after the Flood) equal: as St. <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi> omits three Kings of <hi>Juda,</hi> to keep his <hi>Teſſera</hi> Decad of fourten Generations intire. See the Mans wit: <hi>Matthew</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> intended Genealogy, wherin it matters litle to cut off ſom links of the Chain, ſo the ſucceſſion be kept ſound: but <hi>Moſes</hi> Chronology, which would be utterly uncertain, if any one generation be conceled. St. <hi>Matthew</hi> names the number of <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 1. 17.</note> fourten; but <hi>Moſes</hi> cals them not Patriarchs, nor caſts them into Decads, as he doth the divine Decalog: nay he that looks aright, ſhal ſee eleven in the firſt Age (inroling <hi>Sem</hi> the firſt born) and but 9 in the laſt: nor can any reaſon be rendred to tranſpoſe <hi>Sem</hi> into the later Decad, ſav that it ſo pleaſed the Painter.</p>
            <p>A greater rub reſults, at what age <hi>Terah</hi> begot <hi>Abram:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſ 'tis ſaid, <hi>He lived ſeventy yeers, and begot Abram, Nahor,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. 26.</note> 
               <hi>and Haran, viz.</hi> the eldeſt of them; which many miſdeem to be <hi>Abram,</hi> becauſ firſt named. So is <hi>Sem</hi> in <hi>Noahs</hi> Of-ſpring: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 5. 32.</note> but both for their perſonal dignity being Stock-fathers to Chriſt, and ſeries of the Hiſtory intended by <hi>Moſes:</hi> yet <hi>Japhet</hi> and <hi>Haran</hi> indubitatly eldeſt though laſt named. For <hi>Haran</hi> came of <hi>Terahs</hi> firſt wife, who was father to <hi>Loc, Sarai,</hi> and <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 20 12.</note> 
               <hi>Milcah;</hi> as appeers by <hi>Abrams</hi> anſwer to <hi>Abimelech, That Sarai was his Siſter or Neece, being Daughter</hi> (i. Grandaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) <hi>of his Father, but not of his Mother:</hi> For he and <hi>Nahor</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried their half Brothers daughters. This is the ſtone wherat
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118083:5"/> Chronologers ſtumble, cutting off <hi>(Atropos</hi> like) 60 yeers of the Worlds age: but a ſhort Enthymem ſhal ſoon remov it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Terah</hi> died at 205, when <hi>Abram</hi> was but 75: <hi>Ergo</hi> he was 130 at <hi>Abrams</hi> birth; for 75 and 130 make 205: <hi>Quid bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius, vel quid certius eſſe poteſt?</hi> The proof is irrefragable and indeniable; but the ſhifts deviſed to delud or diſguiſe it ſottiſh and ſenſleſſ: for if <hi>Abram</hi> was begot at <hi>Terahs</hi> age of 70, then <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 11. 31. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 4. What briefer proof can be Or ſurer to agree?</note> was he 135 at his death: if ſo, then was he in <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Egypt,</hi> overcam the four Kings, had <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> his Sons, with many mo acts mentioned from <hi>Gen.</hi> 11 to 22; wherin <hi>Moſes</hi> ſhould be moſt prepoſterous to ſet <hi>Terahs</hi> death 60 years before it befel, and record ſuch geſts after it as were doon in his life time. To elude or evade this evidence, <hi>Scaliger</hi> and his Sectators fain two Journies into <hi>Canaan;</hi> one of <hi>Abram</hi> at 75, in <hi>Terahs</hi> time; another of <hi>Abraham</hi> (when his name was changed) at 135, after his death. This is vented or invent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>gratis</hi> without grounds, and flatly repugns St. <hi>Stephans</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>he cam out of Chaldea to dwel at Charan, and when his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 4.</note> 
               <hi>was dead</hi> (never before) <hi>went into Canaan.</hi> How, or when did he return with a numerous Family (beſide al Cattle, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. 20.</note> and <hi>Lots</hi> company) into <hi>Charan?</hi> or why did one tel him as news, that <hi>Nahor</hi> had a large <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſu <hi>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>z, Buz,</hi> and others) if he had bin ſo latly among them? <hi>Scaliger</hi> brands and blames <hi>Annius</hi> as firſt brocher of this novity (which is a known Verity) that <hi>Terah</hi> begot <hi>Abram</hi> at 130: who though a forger of ſom Fables, ſpeaks truth in this point; nor is he the Inventer of a novity, for <hi>Tertullian,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> and other Antients held it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> He objects. That <hi>Abram</hi> admired how he ſhould beget <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 17. <hi>v</hi> 17.</note> a Son at 100 (which ſom doo even in our dais) <hi>Ergo</hi> 'tis not credible, that <hi>Terah</hi> begot him at 130 yeers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> His doubt roſe from <hi>Sarais</hi> age of 90, becauſ <hi>it ceaſed to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 18 11.</note> 
               <hi>be with hir after the maner of Women;</hi> not from his own decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit diſability: for he had ſundry Sons by <hi>Keturah,</hi> after 140.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> If <hi>Abram</hi> was not born at <hi>Terahs</hi> age of 70, ther is no certainty of the time for connexion of ſacred Chronology.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Yes, his age 75 at <hi>Terans</hi> death, who was 205, provs <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 11. 10.</note> him to be born at his Fathers age of 130: as <hi>Sems</hi> age is notifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Son <hi>Arphaxads</hi> birth; both obliquely, yer infallibly:
<pb facs="tcp:118083:6"/> that <hi>Sem</hi> was 100 yeers old 2 yeers after the Flood. Here al <note place="margin">Note.</note> perſonal Calculation of Times by particular Patriarchs ages ceaſed, and other guids or marks are ſet to comput by: as the Promiſt, Exod, Temple, Reigns of Kings, Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and prophane <hi>Aera's</hi> or Epoches (the Olympiads and <hi>Rome)</hi> which muſt be the future Chronical Cynoſure, wherby to ſteer our Ship in this ſurging Sea.</p>
            <p>The third from <hi>Abrams</hi> birth to the Promiſt, is 75 yeers <note place="margin">3 Stage 75.</note> 
               <hi>Gen.</hi> 12. 4. a plain pregnant place beyond al cavillation or contradiction: yet St. <hi>Stephan</hi> ſaith. <hi>God appeered to him in</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7. 2, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>Chaldea, before he dwelt in Charan, bidding him go eat of his Country, and com into the Land which he ſhould ſhew him.</hi> So the apparition and invitation or injunction, was at <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>r</hi> in <hi>Chaldea</hi> before he cam to <hi>Charan:</hi> but the Promiſſ not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulged til his age 75. when he began his peregrination into <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fourth from the Promiſſ to the Exod and Promulgation <note place="margin">4 Stage 430.</note> of the Law 430. <hi>Exod.</hi> 12. 40 <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. 17. particularized thus. <hi>Abram</hi> out lived the Promiſſ 100. dying at 175. from his <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen</hi> 27 7. <hi>Gen</hi> 35. 28. <hi>Gen.</hi> 25. 26. <hi>Gen</hi> 47. 28 <hi>Gen</hi> 41. 46. <hi>Gen</hi> 45 6. <hi>Gen</hi> 47 28. <hi>Gen</hi> 50 26. <hi>Acts</hi> 7 23. 30</note> death to <hi>Iſaacs</hi> 105. who was 75. when <hi>Abraham</hi> died, and lived 180. which 75. and 105. make 180. from his death to <hi>Jacobs</hi> 27. for <hi>Iſaac</hi> was 60. at <hi>Jacobs</hi> birth, and dying at 180. his Son was 120. who lived 27. more, dying aged 147. from <hi>Jacobs</hi> death to <hi>Joſephs</hi> 54. who was 39. when <hi>Jacob</hi> cam into <hi>Egypt (viz.</hi> 30. when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> dreamed of the Kine, 7. yeers of plenty, and 2. of famin: and <hi>Jacob</hi> lived ther 17. So <hi>Joſeph</hi> was 56. at his death, and lived after him 54. in al 110. from his death to <hi>Moſes</hi> birth 64. which are not preciſely pointed out as the former; but muſt be ſhared betwen his Grand-Father <hi>Coath</hi> and Father <hi>Amram.</hi> From his birth to the Law 80. for he was 40. when he fled to <hi>Madian,</hi> and 40. more at the Exod <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Gen</hi> 15. 13.</note> in al 80. which ſaid ſums (100. 105. 27. 54. 64. 80.) make 430. wherof 215. before <hi>Jacobs</hi> journy into <hi>Egypt,</hi> and 25. after. One ſeeming ſcruple occurs, that God ſaid to <hi>Abram,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7 6.</note> 
               <hi>thy ſeed ſhal ſojourn in a ſtrange Land, and ſhal be il intreated</hi> 400. <hi>yeers: which St. Stephan recites: Ergo</hi> not 430. ſom ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it ſpoken of the total peregrination from the Promiſſ to the Exod complet 430. yeers: but the od 30. omitted in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118083:6"/> 
               <hi>Geneſis</hi> and the <hi>Acts.</hi> This is a remedy worſ then the malady, nor can it conciliat the Texts: for God names the affliction and perſecution of <hi>Abrams</hi> Seed in a ſtrange Land 400 yeers: which many begin at <hi>Iſaacs</hi> birth, being heir of the Promiſſ: but from it to the Law are 405. The moſt orthodox hold, That <hi>Iſaac</hi> being weaned at 5 yeers old, was mocked or il in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 8, 9.</note> by <hi>Iſmael,</hi> which St. <hi>Paul</hi> cals Perſecution, and ther the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 29.</note> 400 commence: but however or whenever the Perſecution of 400 is to begin, which is a diſtinct accompt by it ſelf; we muſt reckon the peregrination with <hi>Moſes</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> from the Promiſſ to the Law ful 430, which is infallible.</p>
            <p>The fifth from the Exod to founding the Temple, involvs <note place="margin">5 Stage 480.</note> 480 ſpecificated thus: <hi>Moſes</hi> ruled in the Deſart 40, dying at 120: <hi>Joſua</hi> 17: <hi>Othniel</hi> 40: <hi>Ehud</hi> 80: <hi>Debora</hi> 40: <hi>Gideon</hi> 40: <note place="margin">1 <hi>Kings</hi> 6. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Abimilech</hi> 3: <hi>Tola</hi> 23: <hi>Jair</hi> 22: <hi>Jephte</hi> 6: <hi>Ibzan</hi> 7: <hi>Elon</hi> 10: <hi>Abdon</hi> 8: <hi>Samſon</hi> 20: <hi>Eli</hi> 40: <hi>Samuel</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> complicat 40: <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 7 36.</note> 
               <hi>David</hi> 40: <hi>Solamon</hi> 4 current, when he began to build: in al 480. Al ſav <hi>Joſua</hi> are literaly Texted: but his reign not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, yet evidently enough implied by leaving him 17 of the 480, ſith the reſt take 463. <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Jo: Lucidus</hi> giv him 25; <hi>Maſſius</hi> 26; <hi>Euſebius</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> 27; <hi>Melancthon</hi> 32; <hi>Cajetan</hi> only 10: but he died at 110 as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did, being 27 <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Joſ.</hi> 24. 29.</note> yeers yonger then <hi>Moſes,</hi> ruling 17 complet (or 18 current) after him.</p>
            <p>Diverſ doubts emerge moſt difficil to aſſoil: for the Iſraelits <note place="margin">Doubts.</note> ſuffred ſundry ſervituds under ſeveral Oppreſſors: as under <hi>Cuſan Richathaim</hi> King of <hi>Armenia</hi> 8 yeers: <hi>Eglon</hi> King of <hi>Moab</hi> 18: <hi>Jabin</hi> King of <hi>Canaan</hi> 20: the Medianits 7: the Philiſtins and Ammorits 18: again the Philiſtins 40: in al 111: which muſt be included in the Judges Regency, or elſ wil ſo far exced the ſaid ſum. After <hi>Samſons</hi> death diverſ acts are recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and 'tis twiſe ingeminated, <hi>in thoſ dais ther was no King in Iſrael:</hi> implying ſom inter-reign or vacancy, to be reckoned in the Rule of <hi>Eli</hi> ſucceding, or elſ wil exced the Accompt. Nay though we ſwalow both thoſ Gudgins in the gulf of Time under the Judges yeers: yet one ſcruple pincheth ſore. St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>God ſuffred their maners in the Wildernes</hi> 40: <hi>afterward he</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 13 18 <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>gav them Judges about</hi> 450 <hi>to the time of Samuel the Prophet:
<pb facs="tcp:118083:7"/> then they deſired a King, and he gav them Saul</hi> (involving Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel) 40 <hi>yeers: and at laſt raiſed up David, &amp;c.</hi> who reigned 40: which ſums 40, 450, 40, 40, and <hi>Salomons</hi> 4.) make 574; being 94 abov the ſaid 480: to which ad <hi>Joſua's</hi> 17 not cited by S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and it amounts to 111 beyond the other: which is the juſt ſum of al thoſ ſervituds, ſeriouſly to be obſerved. To recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile theſe pugnan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> places, is impoſſible: but moſt Interpreters I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magin the prime Amanuenſes or Tranſcribers miſtook 100 yeers, ſetting <hi>tetracoſiois</hi> for <hi>triacoſiois,</hi> 450 for 350; becauſ the Holy Ghoſt is not curious in Genealogy or Chronology: but ſom ſlips in ſuch trifles are tolerated, as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> for Euphony of thriſe 14 Generations, omits 3 Kings after <hi>Ahazaria (Joas, Ahazia, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzia)</hi> beſide Queen <hi>Athalia:</hi> and St. <hi>Luke</hi> ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ads <hi>Cainan</hi> not found in <hi>Moſes</hi> Canon.</p>
            <p>Such anſwers are aſperſions on holy Writ: for if miſpriſions <note place="margin">Cenſure.</note> may paſſ for plea, why may not it be preſumed, that the ſum 480 is 100 too ſhort? for if the 111 ſervile yeers be ſubſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Judges; yet <hi>Joſua</hi> might preſide more then 17, and the Tribe of <hi>Juda</hi> and <hi>Simeon</hi> waged war with <hi>Adonibezek,</hi> took <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Hebron,</hi> with other exploits extant in the two firſt Chapters of <hi>Judges;</hi> before God ſtirred up <hi>Othnie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Yea <hi>Joſephus</hi> records the ſtory of the raviſhed Levits Wife, as doon in thoſ dais, though tranſpoſed <hi>per hyſteron proteron</hi> as a by-buſines; beſide ſom Anarchies intimated after <hi>Samſons</hi> death. How much time theſ things took, is not defined; but muſt be ſhared among the <hi>Judges:</hi> elſ the ſum wil ſwel beyond bounds, which can alow but 40 to <hi>Samul</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> jointly: yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>God gav them Saul</hi> 40: nor can it ſeem much leſſ; ſith he had ſundry Sons valiant Warriers. So little is left for <hi>Samuels</hi> ſole Rule who cam a Child to <hi>Eli,</hi> being dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to God before his birth by his Mother, and ruled long, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very aged. Indeed it appeers not, how long <hi>Eli</hi> lived, yer <hi>Samuel</hi> ſucceded, or how long he Judged yer <hi>Saul</hi> was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: but the ſeries of Story ſhews it to be no ſhort ſpace.</p>
            <p>Laying aſide theſe difficulties, the truth is, That the precited times of Judges are 339: but St. <hi>Paul</hi> caſting in the 111 of Servitud (as the Jews uſed, whoſ accompt he folows) ſaith
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:118083:7"/> 450: ſo his computation including thoſ yeers, and others ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding them materialy agree. This is a fairer juſtification of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> then to correct him under color of Tranſcribers er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: for his ſole ſcope is to ſhew, how God releaſed his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from Bondage, ruling them by <hi>Moſes</hi> and Judges til <hi>Sauls</hi> time: and raiſed up our Lord Jeſus out of <hi>Davids</hi> ſeed, to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle the Scepters ſucceſſion: but intended no exact calculation of Times, ſav what was current among his Countrimen; whoſ Traditions he obſervs often when he ſpeaks to win them. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we muſt hold the 480 in the Book of Kings (wher 'tis purpoſly preſcribed, and the month <hi>Zif</hi> cited) excluding thoſ 111 of oppreſſion, and not ſtick at every oppoſition.</p>
            <p>The ſixth from the Temples foundation to the Captivity of <note place="margin">6 Stage 431.</note> 
               <hi>Babylon,</hi> complet 431 demonſtrated thus: <hi>Salomon</hi> reigned after the building began 36: <hi>Roboam</hi> 17: <hi>Abiam</hi> 3: <hi>Aſa</hi> 41: <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> 25: <hi>Jehoram</hi> alone 4: <hi>Ahazia</hi> 1: <hi>Athaliah</hi> 7: <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> 40: <hi>Amazia</hi> 29: Inter-reign 11: <hi>Azaria</hi> or <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzia</hi> the Leper 52: <hi>Jotham</hi> 16: <hi>Ezekiah</hi> 29: <hi>Manaſſes</hi> 55: <hi>Amon</hi> 2: <hi>Joſias</hi> 31: <hi>Jehoaz</hi> 3 months: <hi>Jehoiachim</hi> 11: <hi>Jehoiachin</hi> or <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coniah</hi> 3 months: <hi>Zedechiah</hi> 11: in al 436, and 6 months: but Chronologers comput only 431. For Nativities are reckoned complet, as one is ſaid to be a yeer old at end therof; but Reigns current, as Kings at firſt day of inchoation cal it the firſt yeer: So King <hi>James</hi> reigned 22 yeers and 3 dais, which is caled 23 current. Now the whol time from <hi>Salomons</hi> fourth yeer A. M. 2994 to <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> captivity A. M. 3425. is juſt 431, and no more. The frequent fractions of Co-reigns, Inter-reigns, and Anarchies are handled by Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh.</hi> Four Babyloniſh <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L. 2 C</hi> 22 § 11</note> Captivities are cited: 1 of <hi>Manaſſes</hi> by <hi>Merodach:</hi> 2 of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoichim</hi> and <hi>Daniel;</hi> but neither of theſ controverted: 3 Of <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 33. 11. 2 <hi>Chr</hi> 36 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 25. 8.</note> 
               <hi>Jeconiah</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel:</hi> 4 Of <hi>Zedekiah</hi> and al the People; al three laſt by <hi>Nebuchadonoſor;</hi> but <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> the grand one <hi>Catexochen,</hi> wher the 70 yeers foretold by <hi>Jeremy</hi> commence in the ninetenth of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> when both City and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were demoliſhed. Many maintain (ſpecialy <hi>Scaliger)</hi> That thoſ yeers begin at <hi>Ezekiels</hi> captivity, becauſ he ſaith, <hi>in the twenty fifth of our Captivity, fourten yeers after the City was ſmiten:</hi> which infers that it began 11 before <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.
<pb facs="tcp:118083:8"/> Indeed his did, but <hi>Jeremies</hi> 70 yeers commenced at the final deſolation, not 11 yeers before. St. <hi>Matthew</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 1. 11. 12.</note> 
               <hi>They were caried to Babylon in Jeconiahs time:</hi> this only provs it to be a Captivity, but not that of 70 yeers. For <hi>Jeremy</hi> is moſt exact herin, deciding the debate beyond al diſpute. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, I wil ſend al the families of the North (ſaith the Lord) and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 25 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nebuchadnezer King of Babel: and wil bring them againſt al Inhabitants of this Land, and the Nations round about, and wil deſtroy them, and make them an aſtoniſhment or hiſſing, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual deſolation. I wil take from them the voice of mirth and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the voice of Bridegroom &amp; Bride; the noiſ of Milſtones, &amp; light of the Candle: &amp; theſ Nations ſhal ſerv the King of Babel</hi> 70 <hi>yeers; but after theſ</hi> 70 <hi>I wil viſit the King of Babel.</hi> So the 70 yeers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin not when this Prophecy was uttered, nor when <hi>Jehoiachim</hi> then reigning was captived, nor in <hi>Jeremiahs</hi> time: but with the utter deluge or devaſtation of City and Country. This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently evinced by the event, wher 'tis ſaid: <hi>They burnt the houſ</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 36. 19. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>of God and broke down the Wal of Jeruſalem: and thoſ left he ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Captiv to Babel; who were ſervants to him and his Sons til the Perſians had Rule; to fulfil the Lords word ſpoken by Jeremy, til the Land had hir fil of Sabbaths. For al the days ſhe lay deſolat, ſhe kept Sabbaths to fulfil</hi> 70 <hi>yeers: but in the firſt of Cyrus, when Jeremies word was accompliſhed, God ſtirred up Cyrus ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, &amp;c.</hi> Both places plainly prov, that they began at <hi>Zedekiahs</hi> grand Captivity: Yea <hi>Daniel</hi> declares, <hi>That God would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 9. 2.</note> 70 <hi>yeers in Jeruſalems deſolation:</hi> So though his own Captivity be reckoned with <hi>Jehoiachims,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiels</hi> with <hi>Jeconiahs</hi> (the People accounting their own ſeveraly) yet the laſt Uuniverſal of 70 yeers, began with the general deſolation of that Nation: therfore the Scaligerians (ſeem they never ſo acut <hi>Lynces)</hi> begin it 11 yeers too ſoon, and abridg the Worlds age ſo much; as they doo 60 mo at <hi>Abrams</hi> birth.</p>
            <p>The ſeventh from the Captivities commencement or incho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation <note place="margin">7 Stage 70.</note> to its accompliſhment or ſolution, compriſeth 70. yeers, warranted by <hi>Jeremies</hi> prophecy: but to light a Candle in the Sun, it may be proved by the reigns of 3. Babyloniſh Kings, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> foretold, <hi>That al Nations ſhal ſerv him, his Son, and</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 27. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Sons Son, til the time of his Land com alſo, and then they ſhal ſerv
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:118083:8"/> themſelfs of him.</hi> Now tho it skils litle, how the 70. yeers be ſorted or ſhared among them: yet moſt probably thus. <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchodonoſor</hi> ſacking <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> in his 19. reigned 25. more, in al 44. <hi>Evilmerodach</hi> 26. <hi>Balthaſar</hi> 17. <hi>Darius Medus</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt 2. which make 70. Then <hi>Cyrus</hi> in his firſt over al <hi>Aſia</hi> (having reigned 23. in <hi>Perſia</hi> before) releaſed the Jews to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>build the Temple. Many adverſ Opinions occur, chiefly <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus</hi> and his numerous Sectiſts, who reckon 5. lineal deſcents, <hi>Nabuchodonoſor, Evilmerodach, Nigliſar, Laboſardach, Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar:</hi> but others make the 3. laſt Brothers and <hi>Evilmero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dachs</hi> Sons; which ſounds neerer to <hi>Jeremies</hi> words, yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tru. For <hi>Balthaſar</hi> was his only Son and next ſucceſſor. Som make <hi>Evilmerodach</hi> and <hi>Balthaſar</hi> Brethren, becauſ <hi>Daniel</hi> cals <hi>Balthaſar Nebuchadnezers</hi> Son for Grandſon, which is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 5 2.</note> uſual in Scripture and al Eaſtern languages. As to <hi>Nigliſar,</hi> he ſeems to be Husband of <hi>Nicotris</hi> (another <hi>Semiramis) Nabuchodonoſors</hi> Daughter, who ruled as Regent part of his 7. yeers madnes, when he ran wild among Beaſts: and <hi>Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſardoch</hi> their Son a ſhort ſpace of 9. moneths, but <hi>Evilmero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dach</hi> as tru Heir enjoied the Crown after his death, and <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaſar</hi> ſucceded. This is the naked truth: but how the 70. yeers are divided betwen them, is not much material; but the groſſ ſum from the grand Captivity to <hi>Cyrus</hi> certain. <hi>Scaliger</hi> led by <hi>Annius</hi> (whom he rejected before about <hi>Abrams</hi> birth in a truth, and now folows him in error) alots to <hi>Evilmero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dach</hi> but 2. yeers, which is far ſhort of verity: for <hi>Jeremy</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 52. 33.</note> 
               <hi>ſhews how highly he favored Jeconiah, who eat bread before him al dais of his life:</hi> which implies no ſhort ſpace; for <hi>Evilme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodach</hi> outlived him being 55. when he was releaſed, and begot <hi>Salathiel</hi> Father to <hi>Pedaiah Zerobabels</hi> Father afterward: ſo his reign muſt needs be much more. <hi>Scaliger</hi> (to juſtify his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the 70. yeers began 11 before <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ruin) allows <hi>Balthaſar</hi> (caling him <hi>Laboſaroach Nicotris</hi> Son) but 5. yeers; making his Father <hi>Nirigliſoroar</hi> Protector for 4. which neer agrees with the 9. months aſſigned by <hi>Annius</hi> to <hi>Nigliſars</hi> Son by <hi>Nicotris:</hi> but both Father and Son ruled ſom part of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchodonoſors</hi> wildnes or woodnes, not ſoly and ſingly after him: therfore he meerly miſtakes the matter being no infallible
<pb facs="tcp:118083:9"/> Oracle. His laſt King (ſuppoſed to be <hi>Balthaſar)</hi> is one <hi>Nabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nidus</hi> whom he cals <hi>Darius Medus:</hi> but differs from his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>Annius,</hi> whoſ <hi>Nabonidus</hi> was a Babylonian like <hi>Balthaſar.</hi> That which deceived him to deem the Beroſian <hi>Nabonidus</hi> the ſame with <hi>Darius</hi> is, becauſ <hi>Daniel</hi> ſaith <hi>Darius</hi> took the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, not won it by force: but 'tis meant that his Son in Law <hi>Cyrus</hi> got it in his abſence, who entred quietly and enjoied it during life. So tho he magiſterialy condemns the whol Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chronologers for holding <hi>Darius</hi> to be Partner (who was Principal) in the Conqueſt; yet are they in the right, and he in evident error. For the <hi>Medes</hi> were Cheiftains, Perſians only aſſiſtants; <hi>Darius</hi> defraier of the charges, and <hi>Cyrus</hi> manager of the wars. So the Acqueſt belonged to <hi>Cyaxares (Daniels Darius Medus)</hi> for 3. reaſons: 1. Becauſ he was <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan</hi> 5. 31.</note> elder and Father in Law to <hi>Cyrus:</hi> 2. Becauſ he began the quarel, and bore al the coſts: 3. Becauſ the Medes then were more famous then the Perſians. Yet the glory is given to <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> for three other cauſes: 1. Becauſ the Perſians magnified their own Monarch, and from them the Greecs hav it: 2. Becauſ he was preſent and Preſident: 3. Becauſ <hi>Darius</hi> dying within two yeers, he was ſeated in the Throne, yer re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mot Nations heard of it: therfore <hi>Darius</hi> cannot be the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſian or Babylonian <hi>Nabonidus,</hi> but he muſt be <hi>Balthaſar.</hi> It is worth obſerving obiter, that <hi>Nabuchodonoſor</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queror <note place="margin">Note wel.</note> of the firſt Monarchy, had only two ſucceſſors of his own loins, <hi>Evilmerodach</hi> and <hi>Balthaſar: Cyrus</hi> next but one, <hi>Cambyſes: Alexander</hi> third ſcarſ one: for <hi>Aridaeus</hi> was his baſe Brother, and his Son <hi>Alexander</hi> by <hi>Roxane</hi> (unborn at his death) barely proclamed by his Grand-mother <hi>Olympias</hi> (as our <hi>Edward</hi> 5.) but ſlain by <hi>Caſſander,</hi> and never Crowned: <hi>Caeſar</hi> the fourth none, but adopted his Siſters daughters Son ſirnamed <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> and he his Wifes Son <hi>Tiberius:</hi> to whom a Nephew <hi>Caligula</hi> ſucceded, and to him an Uncle <hi>Claudius:</hi> who adopted his Wifes Son <hi>Nero</hi> the laſt of <hi>Caeſars</hi> linage, aſwel Adoptitial as Natural. <hi>Sic tranſit gloria mundi.</hi> Thus al four Monarchies ſoon tranſmigred from the Purchaſers pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geny or poſterity to Aliens or Allies: <hi>Man diſquiets himſelf</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſ.</hi> 39 7.</note> 
               <hi>in vain, heaping up riches, and knows not who ſhal gather them.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:118083:9"/> Here ends Canonical Chronography, wherin we had the cleer Sun-ſhine of ſacred Scripture to guid our ſteps; though ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhadowed with thick clouds, which hav bin diſpelled: but muſt henceforth walk by Moon light in the paths of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Hiſtories; having two blazing Torches of the Olympic <hi>Aera</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> to direct us.</p>
            <p>Moſt Men make <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſion of 70 weeks (Annarian, ech <note place="margin">Digreſſion of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſion or Vaticinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> containing a Sabbath of 7 yeers, in al 490) the golden Chain of Chronology from the Captivity to Chriſt; but agree like <hi>Samſons</hi> tail-tied Foxes drawing diverſ wais, both about the initiation and termination: for they are at Daggers point in diverſ Points: 1. What commandment is meant, whether that of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to reedify the Temple, which <hi>Cambyſes</hi> hindred? or of <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis</hi> to finiſh it? or of <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> long hand, one in his ſeventh yeer when he maried <hi>Eſther</hi> to offer in the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 1. 2 <hi>&amp;c. Ezr.</hi> 6. 1. <hi>&amp;c. Ez</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 8 <hi>&amp;c. Neh.</hi> 2. 1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Temple; another in his twentieth, when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> repaired the Wals and City? 2. Whether the 7 weeks and 62 (483 yeers) from going forth of the Decree to <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Prince, determin at his birth, baptiſm, or death? 3. How the laſt week (wherin he ſhal confirm the covenant with many, and in the midſt cauſ the Sacrifice to ceaſ) can be continuat? But leaving contention, let us ſurvey the Viſion ſo much as concerns this intention by a ſhort Paraphraſe to the preſent purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Daniel</hi> in the firſt of <hi>Darius</hi> Conqueſt, finding the 70 yeers <note place="margin">Dan. 9. per totu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> foretold by <hi>Jeremy</hi> neer finiſhed, praied and confeſſed his ſins: <hi>At which time the Angel Gabriel informed, That at beginning of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 22. 23.</note> 
               <hi>his Supplications the Commandment cam forth</hi> (not actualy; for al four were promulged afterward; but by divine Decree which is Yea and Amen) <hi>that</hi> 70 <hi>weeks</hi> (490 yeers) <hi>are determined on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 24.</note> 
               <hi>his People</hi> (the Jews) <hi>and holy City</hi> (Jeruſalem) <hi>to finiſh tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion, ſeal up ſins, reconcile iniquity, bring in everlaſting righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>ſeal up Viſion and Prophecy, and to anoint the moſt Holy;</hi> al applied to Chriſt by moſt Orthodox-Divines. Then he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides theſ weeks: <hi>Know that from going forth of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bring again the People</hi> (this ſeems to imply that of <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus) and to build Jeruſalem</hi> (this rather intends another of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes) to Meſſiah the Prince, ſhal be</hi> 7 <hi>weeks, and</hi> 62: <hi>the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ</hi> 26.</note> 
               <hi>ſtreet ſhal be built and the wal in troublous times</hi> (this <hi>Nehemiah</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:118083:10"/> performed) <hi>and after</hi> 62 <hi>Meſſiah ſhal be cut off, but not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf</hi> (which ſeems to imply his death) <hi>and the People of the Prince that ſhal com</hi> (the Romans) <hi>ſhal deſtroy City and Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, and the end ſhal be with a Flood: and to the Wars end deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are determined:</hi> This befel 38 yeers after Chriſts cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion. <hi>And he ſhal confirm the Covenant with many for one week</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 27.</note> (the laſt) <hi>and in the midſt of it ſhal cauſ the Sacrifice to ceaſ</hi> (hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at Chriſts Paſſion, 3 yeers and half after his Baptiſm) <hi>and for the overſpreading of abominations he ſhal make it deſolat, til the conſummation determined be poured on the deſolat.</hi> This denots the Cities fatal deſtruction, and Temples final demoliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the other half week (for from <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> entry to repreſſ the Rebellion; til <hi>Titus</hi> took <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> were 3 yeers and half) caled by our Saviour the abomination of deſolation, ſpoken by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 15.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet.</p>
            <p>Lo here the literal Eloquy of this Enigmatical Prophecy, the Rack of learned wits; wherin theſ points are cleer: 1. That Meſſiah ſhal expiat ſins, bring in everlaſting Righteouſnes or Salvation, and fulfil al Prophecy. 2. That he ſhal com within thoſ 70 weeks, and in the laſt be ſlain. 3. That the Jewiſh Law and Sacrifice ſhal ceaſ. 4. That both City and Temple ſhal be deſtroied. 5. That this deſolation ſhal be perpetual, til the conſummation of al Things and Times. This confuts Chiliaſts, who ſay Chriſt ſhal in Perſon reign at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> 1000 yeers: but much more the Jews who gape for a Meſſias: For let them begin the 70 weeks wher they wil; it muſt needs be that al theſ things are already accompliſhed, and the Meſſiah com long ago, who hath aboliſhed al Lawiſh Ceremonies.</p>
            <p>For the limits of theſ weeks, ſom begin and end too ſoon: <note place="margin">Opinions.</note> as <hi>Origen</hi> (who reckons 70 yeets for 7 to a week, <hi>viz</hi> 4900) extends them from the Creation to Chriſts Birth. Som begin and end too late: as <hi>Scaliger</hi> and <hi>Junius</hi> from <hi>Joſephus,</hi> who comput from <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis</hi> Decree to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> downfal. Som begin too ſoon and end too late: as <hi>Hippolitus,</hi> who takes riſe 50 yeers before <hi>Cyrus</hi> til Doomſday; and <hi>R. Salomon</hi> who reacheth from the firſt Temples demolition to the ſecunds deſtruction. Som begin too late and end too ſoon: as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon,</hi> who ſets his But at the twentieth of <hi>Longimanus,</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:118083:10"/> Baſis at Chriſts Baptiſm. Som begin right and end too ſoon: Som begin wel and end too late: Som end right but begin too ſoon. Som end wel, but begin too late, as particular inſtances prov. Moſt probably by Commandment is meant <hi>Cyrus</hi> firſt Commiſſion or Proclamation, which <hi>Zerubabel</hi> executed: for ſo ſoon as the 70 yeers of Captivity expired, the 70 weeks of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty (which exced ſevnfold) commenced, and both ſaith <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> are certainly conjoined. 'Tis no leſſ credible, that by abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of deſolation at end of this Viſion, <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ruin by the Romans is underſtood: but from one to the other in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervened 606 yeers (116 abov 70 weeks) which is cauſ that none could ever make their accompts agree, though they rack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Text on tainters, worſ then <hi>Procuſtes</hi> tortured his Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. For in truth the premiſſes infer this reſult, That 'tis no <note place="margin">Reſult.</note> connexion of Times paſt and to come; as the interrupted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervals of 7 weeks, 62, one and half one apertly indicat: but rather a linking together of things treated therin, with refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to Times among themſelfs: as <hi>Cyrus</hi> Command to build the Temple, <hi>Darius</hi> Decree to proſecut it, <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to offer therin, with his Charter to repair the Wals and City: the coming of Meſſiah, his cutting off, not for himſelf; the Covenants conſummation, ceſſation of Sacrifice and Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; with the deſtruction of City and Sanctuary: al which were not doon in 70 ſucceſſiv or continuat Annal weeks, as every ey may ſee. Various are Commentators conceptions, but more erroneous Chronologers computations; which to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile is impoſſible, to refel unprofitable; ſith they unprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly labor in impoſſibles. It ſhal ſuffice to ſhew that it can be no exact or evident rule of Chronology, which only concerns things paſt Hiſtoricaly, not times to com Propheticaly: nor is the <hi>medius terminus</hi> from the Captivity to Chriſt right, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ends at his Birth, Baptiſm, Death, or <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lition; ech of which hav their potent Patrons.</p>
            <p>To conclud, 'tis a Chronical Coordination of Things in it <note place="margin">Concluſion.</note> ſelf, with relation to Times: but no continuat concatination of Times to Chriſt or farther; nor ever ſo intended by the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:118083:11"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si Chronicam ſeriem e Daniele excerpere quaeras;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oceanum exoneras, Aethiopemque lavas.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If Chroniciſm from <hi>Daniel</hi> yee ſeek to draw;</l>
               <l>You drain the Sea, and waſh a Blackmore raw.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tu nihil invita dices facieſve</hi> Minerva.</l>
               <l>Nought ſhalt thou ſay or doo,</l>
               <l>If Nature b'adverſ therto.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>To wreſt a connezion of ſacred Chronology from <hi>Daniels</hi> Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticiny, is to ſwim againſt the ſtream or caſt duſt againſt the wind, which wil fly in thy face. 'Tis impoſſible to make Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verel of a Sows ear, or frame a concatenation of Times contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Holy Ghoſts intention: therfore beat not thy brains to beget or bring forth a new <hi>Minerva,</hi> which al old Midwifes hav faild to effect; not for lack of skil, but 'tis loſt labor to ſow ſeed in a barren ſoil. Sith then no Chonological concordance appeers, and 'tis no part of this Task to explane the Text; we muſt make neceſſity a Virtu, and apply to moſt approved Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors: uſing the ſcale of thoſ two chief <hi>Aeras,</hi> being the beſt Touch-ſtones to try the Truth in dubious points, by way of exact Chronography. Here this Stage had ended, but that Mr. <hi>Livly</hi> (ſomtime Hebrew Lecturer at <hi>Cambridg)</hi> hath ſom ſtrange <note place="margin">In his Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nol. of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian Monarchy</note> ſtrains: whoſ too tedious myſterious expoſition, ſhal put a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riod to this prolix diſquiſition.</p>
            <p>His Tranſlation and Interpretation is this: <hi>Seventy weeks</hi> (Sevenets or Sabbaths of yeers) <hi>are determined</hi> (decreed) <hi>on</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 9 24.</note> 
               <hi>thy People and holy City, to finiſh tranſgreſſion and end ſin</hi> (by Chriſts death) <hi>to make reconciliation for iniquity</hi> (by appeaſing Gods wrath) <hi>to bring everlaſting righteouſnes</hi> (by purchaſing eternal Salvation or Redemption) <hi>to ſeal up Viſion and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy</hi> (by conforming or fulfilling them) <hi>and to annoint the Holy of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Chriſtus, Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, unctus Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonyma.</note> 
               <hi>Holies</hi> (Chriſt Jeſus) <hi>yet Princes, Prieſts, and Prophets were an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed ſingly, but Chriſt al three in one Perſon, being Meſſia Catexochen.</hi> For they were inunct with material Oil only, he with ſpiritual the holy Ghoſt; they being but Types of his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unction. So far he runs with the common current of Divines, but the reſt are novities. <hi>Know then that from going forth of the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 25.</note> 
               <hi>Word</hi> (Decree, Edict, Commandment) <hi>to build again Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118083:11"/> unto Meſſiah the Governour</hi> (by name <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> not Chriſt) <hi>ſhal be</hi> 7 <hi>weeks</hi> (here he makes a Colon to diſ-join them from the 62) <hi>and</hi> 62 <hi>weeks it ſhal be builded again</hi> (continu builded ſo long before it be deſolated) <hi>both ſtreet and wal in a troublous time. And after</hi> 62 <hi>weeks Meſſiah ſhal be cut off</hi> (by <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ.</hi> 26.</note> death, deprivation, exile, or expulſion) <hi>and ſhal hav no being</hi> (as Governor; but expeld as King <hi>Agrippa</hi> was) <hi>and the City and Sanctuary ſhal the People of the com Governor</hi> (the Roman Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler that ſhal com) <hi>deſtroy: and the end therof ſhal be with a Flood</hi> (it ſhal overwhelm the Land as a Deluge) <hi>and to the Wars end</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſ</hi> 27.</note> 
               <hi>ſhal be a preciſe judgment of deſolations</hi> (partly by forren Forces, partly by inteſtin ſeditions in City &amp; Country) <hi>and he ſhal make a ſure Covenant to many one week</hi> (by confirming the things foregoing of Meſſias to be cut off and deſolation; which were fulfild in the laſt week) <hi>and half that week, ſhal cauſ the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and Offring to ceaſ</hi> (in the Temple) <hi>and for the overſpreading of abominations</hi> (by al abominable ſins) <hi>ſhal be deſolation, which to utter preciſe deſtruction</hi> (to dure for ever paſt al reſtauration) <hi>ſhal be poured on the deſolat.</hi> This is the effect of his nice new Paraphraſe on the Text according to the Hebrew toung: but for the inchoation and expiration of theſ weeks, he walks ſingle and ſingular: for de draws the line lower down, making <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius Nothus</hi> (not <hi>Hyſtaſpis)</hi> and <hi>Artaxerxes Mnemon</hi> (not <hi>Longband)</hi> Authors of the ſaid Commiſſions or Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments cited by <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemia. Scaliger</hi> indeed (who is <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L</hi> 6 <hi>de Emend. temp. C</hi> 2.</note> ſtil unhappy to folow the worſt part) imputs the revived De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of building the Temple to <hi>Nothus</hi> ſecund yeer, becauſ from it to finiſhing the Wal and ſtreets were 7 weeks or 49 yeers, when <hi>Nehemiah</hi> returned into <hi>Perſia</hi> in the 32<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Mne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon:</hi> but he rather reſpects Chronical concinnity then Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal verity. For juſt ſo many yeers interceded, but <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſerved his loving Lord <hi>Longimanus,</hi> and returned in his two and thirtieth; which was 60 before <hi>Mnemons</hi> two and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Livly</hi> proceds, That after thoſ 7 weeks, the City was to <note place="margin">His Comment.</note> continu 62 or 434 yeers, and then Meſſiah or Governor of <hi>Judea</hi> (King <hi>Agrippa)</hi> ſhal be cut off or chaſed away with ſtones; and the People of the com Prince or forren Ruler ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:118083:12"/> deſtroy both City and Sanctuary. So he divides the weeks into three parts: 1. From the renewed Decree to build the Temple, in the ſecund of <hi>Nothus</hi> (in truth the ſecund of <hi>Hyſtaſpis)</hi> to <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> Government 49 yeers. 2. From it to the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Commonwealth and Princely Rule, til its ruine (which began in the ninth of <hi>Nero,</hi> when <hi>Albinus</hi> by covetous cruelty oppreſſed the Jews) 62 weeks or 434 yeers. 3. One after the 62, in midſt wherof Meſſias the laſt Ruler ſhal be cut off, as <hi>Agrippa</hi> was pelted out, becauſ he perſwaded the People to obey <hi>Florus</hi> worſ then <hi>Albinus:</hi> and the Jewiſh Government extinct in <hi>Neros</hi> twelfth, abov 3 yeers before their utter deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Thus from the ſecund of <hi>Nothus</hi> when the Decree went forth (as he opines) to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> fatal fal, are 70 weeks, or 490 yeers: indeed 4 more, which is not much. In this ſpace the Roman Rulers <hi>(Caeſtius Gallus, Veſpaſian, Titus)</hi> made Covenants with many Jews that fled to them, uſing them cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly as <hi>Joſephus</hi> informs; which ſundry Rabins take to be the Covenant confirmed for one week: but he expounds it of the new Goſpel Covenant, wherby many ſeing the manifold miſeries of the City and Country foretold by Chriſt, were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted more then any time elſ before. For God warned the Saints (ſaith <hi>Euſebius)</hi> to fly from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (like <hi>Lot</hi> out of <hi>Sodom</hi> to <hi>Zoar)</hi> into little <hi>Pella</hi> beyond <hi>Jordan,</hi> that he might pour his vengeance more fiercely upon Unbeleevers. If any ask to whom the Particle (He ſhal make a Covenant) can be referred ſav to the Roman Ruler? He ſaith 'tis uſual in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew, to underſtand a Perſon or Agent though not expreſſed before, when a tranſitiv Verb hath an Imperſonal notion: <hi>viz.</hi> that before it be deſtroied, a Covenant ſhal be made to the Faithful ther by ſuch Miniſters as God ſhal uſe. In midſt of that week the Legal Sacrifices ceaſed: for at <hi>Veſpaſians</hi> coming the Rebel-Ringleaders aboliſhed the cuſtom of Sacrifices, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing the common People and Country Clowns to be Prieſts (as Coblers, Coopers, Coachmen, and Coſtermongers preach in Tubs during tumults) contrary to Law: yea they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed the Temple, and ſlu the Prieſts at the Altar: ſo in fine no Oblation was offred as <hi>Joſephus</hi> tels: for ceaſing of Sacrifices may apply both to this War and Chriſts death, which aboliſhed
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118083:12"/> and accompliſhed al lawiſh oblations. The ſum is, that by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing the moſt Holy, Chriſt is underſtood: but by Meſſias twiſe mentioned, the Jews Governors <hi>(Nehemiah, Agrippa)</hi> are meant. Wheras then 'tis ſaid 70 weeks are decreed to aboliſh ſin and make attonement, which Chriſt did within thoſ weeks: as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, the work of redemption was perfected under <hi>Tiberius</hi> within <hi>Daniels</hi> 70 weeks.</p>
            <p>The Hebrews held, their Meſſiah ſhould reign at <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction, according to an antient rule of <hi>R. Elias</hi> School, that the World ſhal laſt 2000 yeers before the Law, 2000 under it, and 2000 under Meſſias: which <hi>R. Leviben Gerſhom</hi> cals the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.</note> fifth Kingdom, being to ſucced the four foretold by <hi>Daniel.</hi> For the Law with al Ceremonies ended, when <hi>Titus</hi> razed the ſeat of divine worſhip, and neither Place, Prieſt, nor People left to ſolennize Gods ſervice, <hi>R. Hami</hi> ſaith the Son of <hi>David</hi> ſhal not com ſo long as any Soveraignty remains in <hi>Iſrael: R. Milo</hi> from <hi>R. Eliezer,</hi> that Chriſt ſhal not com, til al Judges and Magiſtrats be clean rid: <hi>R. Moſes Hadarſon</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menteth on <hi>Jacobs</hi> Prophecy, that the Sanedrim ſhal not ceaſ til <hi>Shilo</hi> the Meſſias com: which ſtood in ful authority with <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. 10.</note> the Commonwealth til the laſt war. For <hi>Joſephus</hi> relats, that the high Prieſt <hi>Ananus</hi> and ſeventy Judges condemned <hi>James</hi> (our Lords Brother) Biſhop of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> when <hi>Albinus</hi> began the war: <hi>Agrippa</hi> was expeld not long after: the Sanedrim ſuppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, Prieſthood made a mockery, &amp; al authority turned to anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy: the City and Commonwealth becoming <hi>Acephalon</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Head or Guid. Many ſeek the fulfilling of <hi>Jacobs</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy at Chriſts Birth, becauſ <hi>Herod</hi> an Idumean alien ſwaied the Scepter: but are deceived: for the Jews Government by Prieſts and Elders dured ſtil, tho ſubject to the Romans (as before to Babylonians, Perſians, and Syrians) who ſubſtituted <hi>Herod under them. Onchelos</hi> the Chaldee Paraphraſt interprets it thus: A Magiſtrat of <hi>Juda</hi> ſhal not depart, nor a Scribe of his poſterity til Chriſt com to whom the Kingdom pertains, and al power ſhal be ſubdued to him. Hence ſo many con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfets about the Temples downfal, fained to be Meſſias: yea diverſ Rabbins <hi>(Judas, Nehorai, Nehemias)</hi> took by tradition as tokens of Chriſts coming, that much wickednes ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound,
<pb facs="tcp:118083:13"/> good Men abhorred, and Divinity Schools made Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel houſes; which is <hi>Daniels</hi> overſpreading of abominations. This <hi>Joſephus</hi> records to be at that Siege, when al ſins againſt nature were acted, Laws co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>temned, the Temple deſiled, Virgins deflowred, Matrons raviſhed, Houſes rifled, and al deteſtable crimes perpetrated or practiſed. Thus <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Joſephus</hi> refer the reign of abominations to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction, which the Rabins apply to Chriſts coming. To reconcile al, Chriſts coming is duple: 1. Perſonal in humility, as <hi>Zechary</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Zech.</hi> 9 9.</note> ſaid, <hi>Rejoice daughter of Sion, be glad daughter of Jeruſalem: for lo thy King cometh lowly riding on an Aſſ and an Aſſes Fole.</hi> 2. Powerful in principality, wherof he ſelf ſpeaks, <hi>That ſom</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. 28.</note> 
               <hi>ther ſhould not ſee death, til the Son of Man cam in his Kingdom;</hi> which was verified in St. <hi>John</hi> with others, of whom he ſaid: <hi>If I wil that he tary til I com, what is that to thee?</hi> Who lived <note place="margin">
                  <hi>John</hi> 21. <hi>v.</hi> 22.</note> til <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſolation, when Chriſt cam as a revenging Judg to puniſh his Perſecutors; which may be Meaphoricaly caled a coming: tho diverſ Divines impute it to his Reſurrection, being an entrance into his Kingdom, confirmed by ſending down the Comforter; yet not ſo proper as the other; For <hi>Junius</hi> expounding <hi>Daniels</hi> words <hi>(from going out of the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to build Jeruſalem unto Meſſiah, ſhal be</hi> 7 <hi>weeks and</hi> 62) refers them to Chriſts coming in <hi>Daniels</hi> laſt week, when <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems</hi> deſolation began: becauſ he ſhewed himſelf a ſevere Lord or Judg againſt the Jews, and a gracious Prince or Head of the Church by benefit of the Goſpel. When Chriſt told his Diſciples, that not a ſtone ſhould be left on a ſtone: they asked <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 2. 3.</note> when it ſhould be, and what ſign of his coming, and of the Worlds end? Conjoining the Temples demolition, Chriſts coming, and the Worlds end: but in St. <hi>Marc</hi> and <hi>Luke</hi> they <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Marc</hi> 13. 4. <hi>Luk</hi> 21. 7.</note> only ask what time ſhal be of the Temples ruin? Which ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues, that the Apoſtles held the old Hebrews opinion of the Temples everſion and Chriſts coming to concur; when a change ſhal be of the old Churches overthrow, and coming of Chriſts Kingdom: who expected a new face of things by their Meſſias reign caling it the World to com. As Rabins termed the time from <hi>Adam</hi> to Chriſt the firſt World, and from it to the general Reſurrection the laſt: ſo the Diſciples inquiring the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118083:13"/> ſign of Chriſts coming and the Worlds end; meant the new ſecund World of the Goſpel. Whence thoſe times betwixt Chriſts preaching and <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> periſhing, are caled the laſt dais, and by St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Worlds end. Yea Chriſt anſwering <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 17. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 1. <hi>v</hi> 2.</note> their <hi>Quaere,</hi> givs one token cited by <hi>R. Nehemias,</hi> that wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ednes ſhal multiply, and Charity wax cold. This ſecund com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10 <hi>v</hi> 11. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 12.</note> contains his whol reign, juriſdiction, and judgment in Heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Goſpel preached: even from com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencement of Earthly <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> confuſion, to the general Reſurrection; both being expreſly concluded under his ſecund coming: one reſpecting the inchoation, another the conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the ſelf ſame Kingdom. Thus al circumſtances cohere, wher he ſaith, <hi>This generation ſhal not paſſ til al theſ things be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 34.</note> 
               <hi>fulfilled: and ſom ſhal not taſt of death, til they ſee the Son of Man com in his Kingdom:</hi> which reſpects it beginning in <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalems</hi> fal, when he cam as a revenging Judg; and the reſt relat to the laſt Judgment. For what better concent can be, then that his ſpiritual reign over al Nations by the Goſpel preached ſhould commence, when al Lawiſh Ceremonies ceaſed? Or that the Heavenly Kingdom ſhould begin when the Earthly ended and al Jewiſh Government expired? Or the inward ſubjection of Gods new People the Elect among Gentils, and his ſpiritual ſervice ſhould com in ſtead of the Jews outward worſhip? Or that Celeſtial Sion (new <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem)</hi> ſhould ſucced, when the old Terreſtrials hav no more being? This <hi>Iſaiah</hi> foretold, <hi>It ſhal be in the laſt dais, that the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſai</hi> 2. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Mountain of the Lords houſ ſhal be prepared on the Mountains top, and exalted abov the Hils, and al Nations ſhal flow to it: and they ſhal ſay, com let us go to the Lords Mountain, who wil teach us his wais, and we wil walk in his paths: for the Law ſhal go forth of Sion, and the Lords Word from Jeruſalem.</hi> By the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of his Houſ <hi>(Sion</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem)</hi> is meant Chriſts Church caled the Goſpel, not any real City: w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> cals, <hi>High Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 26. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 22.</note> (new) <hi>Jeruſalem abov, Mother of us al.</hi> This began when the Jews diſpeopled or diſparkled, not before. Indeed Chriſt preached the Goſpel 40 yeers before, &amp; the Diſciples continued it: but the Jews civil Government or Commonwealth, with Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonial
<pb facs="tcp:118083:14"/> Law-worſhip remained ſtil: ſo the preceding preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeemed rather a preparation to Chriſts Kingdom, then a <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat</hi> 4 17. <hi>Mat.</hi> 10 7 23</note> perfect imitation: as he ſelf ſaid, <hi>Amend your lifes, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at hand:</hi> and taught his Apoſtles ſo to doo: implying that his Kingdom was ſhortly to com, yer they ſhould finiſh al the Cities of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> So the ful beginning of his ſpiritual reign is reckoned, when the old government and outward ſervice expired. For then Chriſt reigned alone by his Goſpel (not in any material City) without partnerſhip of the Law, nor could both concur or coexiſt. Thus <hi>Daniels</hi> words of ending ſin and making attonement, may be applied to this time tho ended before: becauſ Chriſt then by a kind of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence or eminence ſanctified his Church from ſin, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled ſinners; when he did it by the Goſpel alone without Law purifyings: and the ſhadow being gon, the body cam in place of it. The bringing in of everlaſting righteouſnes may apply to Chriſt himſelf, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> and St. <hi>Paul</hi> cal him: and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 23 6. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 30.</note> of Viſion and Prophecy to his glorious Kingdom not long after his death, being not fully finiſhed til that time. Laſtly the annointing of moſt Holy, agrees beſt with his abſolut reign: ſo the Hebrews referring it to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſolation, complies with Scripture.</p>
            <p>Now for Chronology: the firſt of <hi>Cyrus</hi> Olymp. 60. 4. <note place="margin">His Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy.</note> when he proclamed the Edict, and ſecund of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> Olymp. 112. 2. when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was ſpoiled (which contain 606. yeers) are generaly made the extrems of this Viſion: in which ſpace ſom go higher, ſom lower for the limits: referring the riſe to <hi>Cyrus</hi> Decree when he licenſed <hi>Zerubabel</hi> to rebuild the Temple; or to the 2 of <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis</hi> when he ratified the former; or to the 7 of <hi>Artaxerxes Longhand,</hi> when he permitted <hi>Ezra</hi> to offer in the Temple; or to his 20, when he ſent <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to reedify wals and City: but the period to Chriſts birth, baptiſm, death, or <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction; as every fancy faſhioneth the Accompts; wreſting words to their ſenſ, yet can make no coherence.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Livly</hi> begins at 2 of <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi> and ends at 2 of <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> which he ſaith is 490 yeers, as indeed it exceds but 4
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118083:14"/> which is neereſt of any for concinnity of comput, but far from truth. For <hi>Hyſtaſpis</hi> (not <hi>Nothus)</hi> licenſed the Jews to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedit the Temple, as <hi>Ezra</hi> evidently ſhews: that when <hi>Zeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez</hi> 4 1, 5, 6, 7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and the Jew began, their Adverſaries hired Counſilors to hinder it al dais of <hi>Cyrus</hi> being abroad in War, and of <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> til the 2 of <hi>Hyſtaſpis:</hi> for <hi>Nothus</hi> did not initiat til 106 yeers after <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and never made any Decree for the Jews. Theſ Men wrot to <hi>Artaſhaſte</hi> (ſo they caled al Perſian Kings, but properly <hi>Cambyſes,</hi> ſtiled before <hi>Ahaſueros</hi> in He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew a Prince being his Fathers Viceroy) who ſtopped the ſtructure 7 yeers in his Fathers abſence, and 7 after. His next <note place="margin">Ez. 5. 1, 2, 3, &amp;c.</note> Succeſſor (ſav 10 months uſurpation by the conterfet <hi>Magi)</hi> was <hi>Hyſtaſpis:</hi> in whoſ 2 yeer <hi>Zerubabel</hi> incoraged by the Prophet <hi>Haggai</hi> and <hi>Zechary</hi> (who were al dead yer <hi>Nothus</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez.</hi> 6. <hi>v.</hi> 6. 13.</note> reigned) retrived the work: but <hi>Tatnai</hi> and <hi>Shetherboznai</hi> oppoſed, til <hi>Darius</hi> charged them to further it, which they ſadly did. So 'tis cleer as Sunſhine, that <hi>Zerubabel</hi> began to build in the firſt of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and revived it in the 2 of <hi>Hyſtaſpis</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter 15 yeers intermiſſion: but he builds on a falſ foundation, that <hi>Cyrus</hi> initiated and made that Edict Olym. 55. 1. for he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan then in <hi>Perſia</hi> (as beſt writers witnes) but not over al <hi>Aſia</hi> til 23 yeers after Olym. 60. 4. which is his meer miſtake or miſpriſion. However if it be granted that <hi>Nothus</hi> made a new Decree, and from it to <hi>Mnemons</hi> 32 be 7 weeks or 49 yeers, and 490 in al to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> devaſtation, neither of which is exactly tru: yet this provs not the Viſion to be a continuation of ſacred Chronology from the Captivity downward: for ther is a vaſt Chaſma of 115 yeers from the 1 of <hi>Cyrus</hi> to the 2 of <hi>Nothus,</hi> not chalked out in thoſ 490 yeers; but denoted by ſecular Authors according to the Olimpic <hi>Aera:</hi> nor can any cleer certain Chroniciſm be collected from the Viſion, as is copiouſly proved.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>W. Ralegh</hi> and many mo begin thoſ weeks at the 7 of <hi>Artaxerxes Longhand</hi> Olym. 80. 2. and end at Chriſts cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixion Olym. 202. 4. which make 490 yeers; yet can be no continued Chronology from the Captivity, ſith neither the
<pb facs="tcp:118083:15"/> preceding time from <hi>Cyrus</hi> to <hi>Longimanus;</hi> nor the ſubſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent from our Saviours ſuffering to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (both which belong to the Viſion) is involved ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Livly</hi> ſeeks to confirm or countenance his novities by <note place="margin">Opinions.</note> Conteſtees: 1. <hi>Euſebius,</hi> who by Meſſiah twiſe named under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands a Succeſſor of annointed high Prieſts, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> Ruled Regaly (as the Machabees and others) after their releaſ from <hi>Babylon:</hi> ſo the Hebrews take the word, and expound cutting off by expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion or otherwiſe. 2. <hi>Tertullian,</hi> who begins the 70 weeks at the ſecund of <hi>Darius,</hi> naming his 4 Succeſſors <hi>(Mnemon, Ochus, Arſes, Codomon)</hi> which muſt needs be <hi>Nothus,</hi> though he miſcals him <hi>Medus.</hi> The end of thoſ weeks he ſets in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund of <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> ſaying, that the Jews by being ſubdued, ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled <hi>Daniels</hi> 70 weeks. 3. <hi>Sulpitius Severus</hi> St. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporar, who ſaith the Jews by <hi>Cyrus</hi> leav began the Temple, but were hindred about 100 yeers; recompting <hi>Cambyſes, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Xerxes, Artaxerxes</hi> (with another <hi>Xerxes</hi> and <hi>Sogdianus)</hi> who al prohibited the progreſſ: then <hi>Darius (Nothus)</hi> in whoſ ſixth yeer it was finiſhed. From thence to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal he reckons 69 weeks or 483 yeers, as <hi>Daniel</hi> prophecied. 'Tis tru the inchoation of that deſolation <hi>Albinus</hi> made about the time ſpecified, but the conſummation befel 7 yeers after. 4. <hi>Scaliger</hi> refers the beginning of thoſ weeks to <hi>Nothus</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, and end to <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> deſtruction. So <hi>Junius</hi> computs from the ſecund of <hi>Nothus</hi> to the ſecund of <hi>Veſpaſian:</hi> with whom concur <hi>Clemens Alexand: Origen, Chryſoſtom,</hi> and ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry Rabins: nor can thoſ Sevenets (divided into 7, and 62, and one) be more properly or probably interpreted. Thus he pleads bravly in a bad Cauſ.</p>
            <p>How <hi>Euſebius</hi> or the Hebrews expound the word <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> 
               <note place="margin" type="runSum">Anſwer.</note> concerns not Chronology: but al Orthodox Divines apply it to Chriſt. <hi>Tertullian</hi> contradicts himſelf, naming <hi>Darius Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> and noting out <hi>Nothus:</hi> for thoſ Antients were ſory Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorics and worſ Chronologiſts. <hi>Sulpitius</hi> ers in ſaying the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding was hindred 100 yeers: for <hi>Zerubabel</hi> began and ended
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:118083:15"/> it in 20. <hi>Scaliger</hi> was <hi>Joſephus</hi> Son to <hi>Julius,</hi> both ſelf-ſingular: he by Meſſiah to be ſlain after 62 weeks, underſtands Chriſt; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning at the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Mnemon</hi> (when he ſaith <hi>Ezra</hi> was ſent) &amp; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ez</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 7.</note> ending at the Paſſion: but this cannot cohere: for <hi>Ezra</hi> went in the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>Artaxerxes Longhand,</hi> nor doo the yeers jump; ſith our Saviour ſuffred by general ſuffrage of beſt Authors Ol. 202. 4. when <hi>Phlegon</hi> reports an extraordinary Eclipſ of the Sun to happen at ſixth hour or high noon, that Stars ſhone as at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night; and an Earthquake ſubverted ſundry Houſes at <hi>Nice</hi> in <hi>Bithynia;</hi> which the Evangeliſts ratify touching a deep darknes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 27. 45. <hi>Marc.</hi> 15. 33.</note> from the ſixth hour to the ninth at ful Moon, when can be no Solar Eclipſ, but at New. <hi>Daniel</hi> divides the weeks into 7 at building the Wals, 62 for continuance, and one after: who then can conceiv but 62 ſhal immediatly ſucced the 7, and preced the one? if ſo, then they muſt commence in <hi>Mnemens</hi> 32, and end 7 yeers before <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> everſion. Again, 'Tis ſaid the City ſhould be built (ſtreets and Wal by <hi>Nehemiah)</hi> 62 weeks, and then Meſſiah be cut off and the City confounded: how then can it be made good that Chriſt ſhal be ſlain after thoſ 62? ſith <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> floriſhed after Chriſts crucifixion 30 yeers yer the broils began, and 37 before the deſolation determined. Thus theſ Men tug and toil to patch up a ſeeming Chain of Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, but fal at ods like a viperous brood of Cadmean Brethren, til they tear ech other in peeces; yet can never effect their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended project.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oceanum exoneras, experto crede</hi> Roberto:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Si quaeras Chronicos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e</hi> Daniele <hi>Chores.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Beleev tried <hi>Robin,</hi> you the Ocean drain;</l>
               <l>Who Chroniciſm ſeek from <hi>Daniel</hi> al in vain.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Now to the task.</p>
            <p>The eghth from the Captivities ſolution, to the Perſian Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchies <note place="margin">8 Stage 207.</note> expiration involvs 207 yeers. Al Authors agree, that
<pb facs="tcp:118083:16"/> 
               <hi>Cyrus</hi> initiated in <hi>Perſia</hi> Olym. 55. 11. and over <hi>Aſia</hi> 23 yeers after Ol. 60. 4. which concurs with <hi>Romes</hi> 216: but <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> vanquiſhed <hi>Darius</hi> at <hi>Arbela</hi> and won the Perſian Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion Ol. 112. 3. A. U. 423, which caſt 207: the perſonal reigns ratify it thus. <hi>Cyrus</hi> 7, <hi>Cambyſes</hi> 7, <hi>Magi</hi> 1, <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis</hi> 36, <hi>Xerxes</hi> 21, <hi>Artaxerxes Longhand</hi> 40, <hi>Xerxes</hi> 2, and <hi>Sogdianus</hi> (ſuppoſed to be <hi>Eſthers</hi> Sons) 1; <hi>Darius Nothus</hi> 19, <hi>Artaxerxes Mnemon</hi> 43, <hi>Ochus</hi> 23, <hi>Arſes</hi> 3, <hi>Darius Codoman</hi> 6, in al 207, as the particulars comput. This is the beſt Accompt moſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and ſutes beſt with both Epoches, which we muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly obſerv.</p>
            <p>The ninth from ſuppreſſion of the Perſian, to ſubverſion of <note place="margin">9 Stage 163.</note> the Macedonian Monarchy in King <hi>Perſeus,</hi> are 163. For he was caried Captiv to <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Macedon</hi> made a Province O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: 153. 2. A. U. 586, which jump with the ſaid ſum, and may be ratified by the ſeveral reigns: <hi>viz. Alexander</hi> after his Perſian Conqueſt 7, <hi>Aridaeus</hi> 6, <hi>Caſſander</hi> 19, his two Sons <hi>(Antipater</hi> and <hi>Alexander)</hi> 4, <hi>Demetrius</hi> 6, <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> 7 months, <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> 5 yeers, <hi>Seleucus</hi> 7 months, <hi>Ptolomaeus Ceraunus, Antipater, Meleager, Soſthenes</hi> confuſedly 2, <hi>Antigonus Gonatas</hi> 36, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrius</hi> 10, <hi>Antigonus Doſon</hi> 12, <hi>Philip</hi> 42, <hi>Perſeus</hi> 12, in al 163. This may be confirmed by the Syrian and Egyptian reigns (the two laſt Reliques of <hi>Alexanders</hi> immenſ ſpoils) if need were.</p>
            <p>The laſt from diſſolution of the Perſian Monarchy to Chriſts <note place="margin">10 Stage 166.</note> Nativity, are 166; which may be deduced from the Jewiſh Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and Kings of Egypt: but the Olympic <hi>Aera</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> ſhal ſuffice, For from <hi>Perſeus</hi> Olym. 153. 2. A. U. 586 forecited, to Chriſts Incarnation Olym. 194. 4. A. U. 752 (being the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 3. 1. 23.</note> fourty ſecund of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> a Minorit calculats from St. <hi>Luke)</hi> are juſt 166 yeers. For <hi>Jul. Caeſar</hi> was ſlain in Senat <hi>Mar.</hi> 15. A. U. 710. and <hi>Auguſtus</hi> reigned after him 42 when Chriſt was born A. U. 752. So al the ſaid ſums pointly cohere; which ſhal be caſt jointly together: 1656, 353, 75,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118083:16"/> 430, 480, 431, 70, (theſ ſeven from infallible di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Oracles, the three ſubſequent from beſt helps of Human Hiſtory and Chronology) 207, 163, 166 in total 4031 current, or 4030 complet: <hi>ſic conſtant computa noſtra:</hi> which ſhal be the conſtant baſis or confident groundwork of al inſuing Marginal Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſms.</p>
            <p>Seek not to wreſt a connexion of ſacred Chronology from <hi>Daniels</hi> Vaticiny, which the holy Ghoſt never in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended: Swim not againſt the ſtream, nor caſt duſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the wind, leſt it fly in thy face. 'Tis impoſſible to make Points of a Pigs tail, or to frame a cleer concatena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of times paſt with thoſe to com, wher no ſuch matter appeers.</p>
            <p>Let the Summary ſtand immutable 4030 complet. complet. <note place="margin">Summary.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Beſide ſuch as folow the depraved Septuagints, ſom <note place="margin">Corollary.</note> others exced this ſum: as <hi>Alphonſus</hi> reckons 5984: <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philus Antiochenus</hi> 5476: St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> 5351: <hi>Iſidor</hi> 5210: <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Oroſius</hi> 5190: <hi>Metheodorus</hi> 5000: 4192 <hi>R. Moſes Germediſ</hi> 4058: but many mo (ſpecialy Scaligeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans) fal ſhort, who pitch moſtly about 3960 ſom more, ſom leſſ: which being numberleſſ, ſhal go nameleſſ. Theſ fail 60 yeers at <hi>Abrams</hi> birth, caſting it in the ſeventieth of <hi>Terahs</hi> age, and 11 at the grand Captivity, commencing it when <hi>Jehoiachim</hi> or <hi>Jakim</hi> was captived, which are evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent errors. Howbeit if the precited parcels of 111 ſervil yeers ſwalowed in the Judges Regency; with the incertain Interreigns, vacancies, and Anarchies (beſide the Elders Rule after <hi>Joſua</hi> yet <hi>Othniel</hi> Judged; omitting <hi>Samuels</hi> ſole ſway) be wel ſcanned; ther wil be more cauſ to ſubnect many then ſubtract any from the ſaid 4030: but the 60 yeers and 11 wherin the Scaligerian Faction fails, being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to their ſum 3960, make up 4031 current, as here fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:118083:17"/>
            <p>Chronology is the darkeſt peece of liberal literature, and <note place="margin">Valediction.</note> Chronography the difficileſt point of Chronology: but this a main Maſter-peece, which hath coſt much induſtry to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet it; beſide moſt exact exerciſe of Intellect and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to contriv it into this form or fabric. 'Tis a litle Lamp, which may giv light enough to lead vulgar Readers through the crooked corners of this Chronical Labyrinth: wherin every one may eaſily apply the yeer of Chriſt from time to time: but to buſie their brains about needleſſ Queſtions, ſenſleſſ Opinions, endleſſ Diſſertations, and fruitleſſ Diſqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, wil be loſt labor too late repented: ſuch as this Chronography cannot ſatisfy, may go farther and fare worſ.</p>
            <p>The four principal <hi>Aeras</hi> ſet in the Margins, are that of the World, which began the firſt day of Creation, when God made the Chaos: that of the Olympiads (which take name of the City <hi>Olympia</hi> neer <hi>Elis,</hi> wher <hi>Jupiters</hi> Temple ſtood) commenced in the fiftieth of King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zzia</hi> A. M. 3255 when Prince <hi>Iphitus</hi> renewed thoſ Games, inſtituted by <hi>Hercules Alcmenus</hi> in <hi>Gideons</hi> Judgſhip 500 yeers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore: that of <hi>Rome</hi> beginning 25 yeers after in the eghth of King <hi>Ahaz</hi> A. M. 3280: A. O. 7. 1. That of Chriſt commencing at his birth, A. M. 4031. A. O. 194. 3. A. U. 752. The firſt is Charactered A. M. the next A. O. the third A. U. the laſt A. C. The firſt and laſt are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred the one taken from the old Teſtament, the other from the New; the two midmoſt ſecular; one uſed by the Greecs, the other by the Romans: but both ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>refragable, if rightly applied or uſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aera</hi> ſo oft cited in Chronology, is a Plural of <hi>Aes</hi> (ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying <note place="margin">Supplement.</note> ſmal peeces of braſſ wherwith men caſt Accompts) but uſed by Catechreſtic Soleciſm (maugre <hi>Priſcians</hi> pate) in the Singular number for the Head, But, or Beginning of any Chronical Computation; wherof ſundry Nations hav ſeveral ſorts. The Hebrews uſed three chiefly, the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118083:17"/> Creation, <hi>Abrams</hi> birth, and <hi>Egypts</hi> Exod: beſide Flood, Promiſſ, Temple, Captivity of leſſ mark. The Aſſyrians or Babylonians, from King <hi>Nabonaſſer alias Salmonaſſer.</hi> The Perſians from King <hi>Cyrus</hi> and King <hi>Jezdegerd.</hi> The Greecs from <hi>Troy</hi> taken, and Olympic Games. The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans from their Cities foundation, and <hi>Auguſtus Caeſars</hi> inauguration. Mahometans from their Pſeudoprophets <hi>Hegira</hi> or flight from <hi>Mecha.</hi> Chriſtians in general from Chriſts Nativity current <hi>Januar.</hi> 1. but the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> (with <hi>Piſa</hi> and <hi>Siena</hi> in Italy) from his Conception or Incarnation <hi>March</hi> 25: we taking it complet or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummat, when he had bin a whol yeer in the fleſh, though but three months old: they current or inchoat from the firſt day of Conception (as Kings reckon from their initi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation) ſo they date 9 months before the Vulgar, and a whol yeer before us: which is a difference in the maner, but al e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualy tru for the matter; and the very ſtile diſtinguiſheth the form: For our term is <hi>A<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. ab Incarnatione</hi> implying com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plet, theirs <hi>Annus Incarnationis</hi> importing current. <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi> and <hi>Siena</hi> ſtile this yeer <hi>Annus Incarnationis</hi> 1655: we <hi>ab Incarnatione</hi> 1654: but al elſ cal it <hi>Annus Nativitatis</hi> 1654, commencing at Chriſts Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion laſt paſt.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The tru meaſure of a Natural Solar yeer, and a civil Julian or Soſigenean.</head>
               <p>A Tru Yeer is the Suns total race or revolution <note place="margin">Note.</note> through the Zodiacs 12 parts, from any one point to the ſame: which is finiſhed in 365. Natural dais, 5 Equinoctial hours, 49 minuts, and 16 ſecunds: a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cund being the 60 part of a minut, that the 60 of an hour, and this the 24. of a Natural day, as is vulgarly known.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:118083:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Julius Caeſar Romes</hi> perpetual Dictator and Emperor, by adviſe of <hi>Soſigenes</hi> an Egyptian Aſtronomer, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed the Roman Calendar then variouſly embolized more or leſſ at the Prieſts or Augurs pleaſures; reducing the yeer to a ſet period of 365 dais and 6 hours (or a quarter of a day) complet: allowing one day <hi>(Febr.</hi> 24) to be added every 4 yeer, in leiu of thoſ od annal hours: which exceds the Solar 10 minuts and 44 ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunds every yeer; and we obſerv it unaltered ever ſince. This ſurpluſage (which <hi>Caeſar</hi> compted as an Atom not conſiderable) makes one intire day (lack one minut and 44 ſecunds) in 134 yeers: ſo that from Chriſts birth hav reſulted or increaſed ful 12 dais with 8 hours, which ſhould be abated or taken back, to bring every day in the ſet ſtation or ſeaſon it was then. For by this obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, the 12 laſt dais of ech moneth, poſſeſſ the place of the nexts 12 firſt; which is a Turciſh Soleciſm in Chroniciſm: who from the old Egyptians obſerv a Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nar yeer of 12 New Moon changes, containing 354 dais: which is 11 and a quarter ſhorter then our Julian. So they run back in Crablike Poſt (as we crawl or creep forth with Snaillike pace) and in 18 yeers keep Summer months at Winter or contrarily: not heeding in what ſeaſons they ſolennize their falſ Feſtivals: but Chriſtians ſhould be more careful to celebrat tru in their juſt times, ſo neer as can be collected by reaſon or record.</p>
               <p>Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> 13 at <hi>Trent</hi> Council, conſulted <hi>Aloyſius Lilius</hi> with other Mathematicians how to rectify this dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity, and finding that at firſt univerſal Synod of <hi>Nice, Sol</hi> entred <hi>Aries</hi> the Equinox day <hi>March</hi> 21 (which then <note place="margin">A. C. 325.</note> befel <hi>Mar.</hi> 11) he with the Tridentin Fathers ſubtracted or ſtruck off 10 dais on <hi>Octob.</hi> 5. 1582: but ſhould hav defalked 2 more (to reach Chriſts birth) as <hi>Lily</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, being two dais deficient ſtil. Yet to keep this correction firm and free from error for ever, they ordered or ordeined to hav one leap-day omitted every 100 yeer,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:118083:18"/> except the 400 becauſ thoſ 10 redundant minuts and 44 ſecunds, make up neer about 3 whol dais in 400 yeers; which was a wary <hi>Proviſo</hi> or warrantabe Prevention of error for the future.</p>
               <p>The firſt Reformation is clyped the Julian Soſigenean yeer, the laſt (which is no new Accompt, but a neceſſary Note or Comment on the former) the Gregorian Lilian: but both Roman, one Imperial, the other Papal, and both ſomwhat erroneous. This laſt moſt Chriſtian Stats (Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants and Papiſts) folow being no point of Religion, but civil computation by the notion of <hi>ſtilo novo:</hi> who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract their Anniverſary deviation in part (tho not pleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarily or perfectly) and prevent future aberrations. Why then ſhal we ſtick ſtil in the Suds, and ſtand ſingle or ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular in evident error? Specialy ſith by uniform confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity with them, the duple comput of <hi>ſtilo veteri &amp; novo</hi> wil be cancelled or caſhired, to the ineffable benefit of common commerce in this Commonwealth with forren Nations.</p>
               <p>Such a ſudden ſimultal ſurreption of 10 or 12 dais, wil breed or beget much confuſion and contention here con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Contracts, Covenants, Bonds, Bils, dates of Deeds, paiment of Rents, &amp;c. but if al Biſtextil dais be forbid or forborn for 44 yeers (which wil meet with the forren, when by ſuperſeding a leap-day A. C. 1700 they wil be 11 dais before us) or 52 according to the Suns ſtation in Chriſts age, which wil bring us 2 dais before them: a gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Reformation wil inſenſibly inſu, without the leaſt inconvenience to be imagined. For what damage or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triment can acru ora riſe to any, if al yeers run equal ſo long? The maner may be effected by Act of Parlement in few words: that no Leap-yeer ſhal be held in <hi>England</hi> for 44 yeers (or 52 as ſhal ſeem beſt) next coming: but afterward to be kept as before, except every 134 yeers for ever: or elſ, but afterward one leapday ſhal be ſtruck off every 100 yeer (except ech 400) for ever: either of which
<pb facs="tcp:118083:19"/> Proviſo's is authentic to keep it right. For the ſaid redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance complets one day in 134 yeers (lack only one minut, 44 ſecunds) and 3 dais in 400, lack 26 minuts and 40 ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunds: which make one day in 24000 yeers being incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Al Solar ſeaſons (the 2 Equinoxes, 2 Solſtices, &amp;c.) keep the ſelf ſame ſet ſtations conſtantly and continualy: but civil computations of things doon on ſuch a day cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain (as Chriſts Birth <hi>Decemb.</hi> 25 A. M. 4031 current, the <hi>Norman</hi> Conqueſt of <hi>England Oct.</hi> 6. A. C. 1066) run on one day too far every 134 yeers, as foreſhewed: ſo Chriſts birth is 12 dais later then it ſhould be and the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt 4. Thus I hav doon my duty or devoir to denote and demonſtrat the tru dimenſion of a Solar yeer, the Julian deviation, Gregorian aberration, motivs, means, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of rectification obvious to every common capacity: al which I humbly ſubmit to ſuperior cenſure.</p>
               <p>Thus hav I like a long wearied Pilgrim, tired my head <note place="margin">Upſhot.</note> to diſquite the truth of Times, toiled my hands to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it often, and dulled my Pen to ſatisfy or gratify the cenſorious Surveiors; who wil rather repay ſcofs and ſcorns, then du praiſes or thanks: But I expect no better reward then what common Writers attain, and hav doon my beſt indevors to inſtruct or inform the Ignorant: let the Learned learn to emend it, who may take exemple by the Premiſſes, to poliſh or perfect this new deviſed Art by bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paterns.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Lector, habe Chronica haec; quae ducta ab origine Mundi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad tua ſunt filo ſecula nexa brevi.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad Chriſti geneſin primaevi tempora Mundi,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Hocce Chronographicum ſingula ſignat Opus.</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Aliter.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tempora deducit de cunis ſingula Mundi,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Alias</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad Chriſtum haec natum Chronnographia brevis.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad Chriſtum genitum, a prima ſcaturigine Mundi,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Secus.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Quaeque ſua hoc ſerie ſecula Monſtrat Opus.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:118083:19"/>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tela Chronographica haec a Mundi fronte gradatim,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Sive.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ad Chriſti tempus, tempora reſque refert.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>De certo Anno Mundi, quo natus eſt Chriſtus.</head>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Mille quater Mundi a geneſi lapſi atque triginta</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">A. M. 4030.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Sunt Anni, ut Chriſtus carne repertus erat.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Bis duo mille Anni &amp; decies ter ab Orbe creato:</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Alias.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Filius ante Dei quàm Caro factus erat.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Reader, theſ Chronographs with a ſhort thred wrought, </l>
                  <l>From the Worlds dawning to thy dais are brought. </l>
                  <l>This Chronographic Work from the Worlds prime, </l>
                  <l>Shews til Chriſts Birth the tru Accompt of Time. </l>
                  <l>From the Worlds Cradle, this brief Chronography </l>
                  <l>Draws down al Times to Chriſts Nativity. </l>
                  <l>From the Worlds riſe to Chriſts birth Stage by Stage, </l>
                  <l>This Work in order ſets forth every Age. </l>
                  <l>This Chronographic web from the Worlds Spring, </l>
                  <l>Til Chriſts time ſhews the Times and every thing. </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <head>The tru yeer of the World, wherin Chriſt was born.</head>
                  <l>From the Worlds birth, four thouſand thirty yeers cleer</l>
                  <l>Ran out; when Chriſt did in the fleſh appeer. </l>
                  <l>From the World made four thouſand yeers and thriſe ten </l>
                  <l>Paſt; yer Gods ſole Son was made Fleſh like Men. </l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <trailer>AN END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="authors_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:118083:20"/>
            <p>THis Libel or litle Book is a peculiar Brat of my ſole <note place="margin">Adviſe.</note> Brain, or proper Bird (a Lark) of my Perſonal Brood; who like a Spider ſpun this whol Web out of mine own Bowels: which hath many unvulgar myſteries never vented or invented before: <hi>Loquendum cum Plebiis, ſcribendum cum Eruditis; ſed ſentiendum cum Sophis ſeu Sapientibus.</hi> I divulge likewiſe two Pedetaſters: <hi>viz.</hi> an Enchiridion of Epigrams in Latin and Engliſh Meters: And alſo eght Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical Theorems, with ſom Supplements ſubjoined: the price of both together at Preſſ being 4 s. 6 d. as ſhal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peer in the Title Pagin of ech. This litle Book may be bound with the laſt of thoſ two, if any ſo like, being both of one Paper and Letter.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
